Guide to the McKeen-Duren Family Papers, 1720-1945 and undated, bulk 1855-1900
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McKeen-Duren Family papers 1720-1945 and undated, bulk 1855-1900
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McKeen-Duren family
12.6 linear feet Extent: 3240 Items
Two related families of ministers and educators living in New England and the Midwestern United States. The McKeen-Duren Family Papers span the dates 1720-1945, with the bulk of the material covering the period between 1855 and 1900. The papers are arranged into the following series: Correspondence, the largest series; Diaries and Scrapbooks; Financial Papers; Genealogy; Legal Papers; Photographs; Printed Materials; Writings; and Oversize Material. The Writings series is divided into two subseries, Manuscripts and Volumes. There are many boxes of correspondence spanning the years 1816-1934, with a large section dating from the Civil War. The Photographs Series is also large and offers many fine examples of 19th century photographic processes, including ambrotypes, cyanotypes, daguerreotypes, tintypes, albumen prints, cartes de visite, and early gelatin silver or platinum prints. As a whole, the collection serves as a rich source of detail on the debates on statehood and the abolition of slavery, the Civil War, religion in New England, literary and educational traditions in the 19th century United States, 19th century New England society, and the history of the McKeen-Duren families from the 1700s to the 20th century.
RL.00875
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The McKeen-Duren Family Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1973.
Biographical Notes
The McKeen family traces its history to James McKeen, a magistrate, who immigrated to America from Northern Ireland in the early eighteenth century (circa 1718) and was active in the settlement of what would come to be called Londonderry, New Hampshire.
James McKeen, 1666-1756
Emigrated from Ireland to America in 1718. Settled in township of Londonderry, New Hampshire, circa 1719. Commissioned as magistrate in 1720.
Silas McKeen, 1791-1877
Great-grandson of James McKeen. Born in Corinth, Vermont. Married Phebe Fuller in 1816; she died in 1820. Children: Marianne, Serena, and Julia. Married Hannah Johnson in 1821. Children: Philena, Catherine, and George, and Phebe, his last child. Only two daughters survived into old age, Philena and Phebe. Second wife Hannah died in a carriage accident in 1848. Married Sarah Parmelee, 1851. Congregational Minister of Bradford, Vermont (1814-1832?, 1842-1866). Born in South Corinth, Vermont, and died in Bradford. Ordained, 1815. M.A., Dartmouth, 1822. Called to be pastor in Belfast, Maine, 1832. Called once more to Bradford, 1842-1866. Received D.D. from Dartmouth, 1861. Wrote many pieces for the The Vermont Chronicle, The Bradford Vt., The New Englander, and The Green Mountains Freeman, including memorial pieces, obituaries, and articles and published letters on temperance, and defending the abolition of slavery (1830s-1850s). Wrote A Scriptural Argument in Favor of Withdrawing Fellowship From Churches and And Ecclesiastical Bodies Tolerating Slaveholding Among Them (New York: American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society, 1848).
Serena McKeen Duren, 1819-1862
Daughter of Silas McKeen and Phebe Fuller McKeen. Married Rev. Charles Duren, 1841. Two daughters, Marianne and Elizabeth, died in childhood. Mother of Charles McKeen Duren (1842-1934).
Philena McKeen, 1822-1898
Daughter of Silas McKeen and Hannah Johnson McKeen. Helped to establish Abbot Academy (sister institution of Phillips Academy), Andover, Massachusetts, and served as principal for 33 years. Co-author with her sister Phebe of Annals of Fifty Years: A History of Abbot Academy, Andover, Mass., 1829-1879 (1880).
Phebe Fuller McKeen, 1831-1880
Daughter of Silas and Hannah McKeen. Long-time teacher at Abbot Academy. Author of numerous published writings including several book-length works: Thornton Hall (1872); Theodora (1875, entitled Theodora Cameron when published in the United Kingdom circa 1878); The Little Mother and her Christmas (1876); Annals of Fifty Years: A History of Abbot Academy, Andover, Mass., 1829-1879 (1880, coauthored with her sister, Philena); and Sketch of the Early Life of Joseph Hardy Neesima (1890, published posthumously). Published many short pieces under the pseudonym Jenny Bradford.
Charles McKeen Duren, 1842-1934
Grandson of Silas McKeen and son of Serena McKeen Duren and Rev. Charles Duren. Moved from New England to Iowa after the Civil War. Married Gertrude Whiting. Children: Alice Serena (Fanny?) and Mabel. Began successful career in banking in Iowa and worked to establish banking services in underserved areas.
Note
More information on Silas McKeen family members can be found in Silas McKeen's book, A History of Bradford, Vermont (digitized and availabled online). Also, additional biographical information on the McKeen, Fuller, and Duren families and related individuals, as well as further details on the photographic components of this collection, are available in the Rubenstein Library; please contact a reference archivist for assistance. Finally, the numerous genealogical documents in this collection can be consulted.
Collection Overview
The McKeen-Duren Family Papers span the dates 1720-1945, with dates on the majority of the items falling between 1855 and 1900. The materials in the collection document in great detail the histories of the members of these two New England families of educators, ministers, writers, and abolitionists, with the focus primarily on the McKeens. The papers are arranged into the following series: Correspondence, the largest series; Diaries and Scrapbooks; Financial Papers; Genealogy; Legal Papers; Photographs; Printed Materials, which includes clippings and ephemera; Writings, divided into volumes and manuscripts; and finally, there is a small group of Oversize Materials. The photographs series is large and offers many fine examples of 19th century photographic processes, including ambrotypes, cabinet cards, cyanotypes, daguerreotypes, tintypes, albumen prints large and small, cartes de visite, postcards, and early gelatin silver printing-out images or platinum prints. Most are individual portraits but there are also interiors of family rooms and images of educational institutions. Topics of note documented across all the series include religious thought and institutions in New England, the education of women and the careers of female educators, photography in the 19th century, the Civil War and its effects on New England society, westward migration patterns, social life in Massachusetts and Vermont, family relations in the 19th century, 19th century New England women writers and their activities; and New England genealogy. There are also many clippings in the scrapbooks debating the abolition of slavery, many written by Silas McKeen. As a whole, the collection serves as a rich source of detail on 19th century New England social life and customs, and the history of the McKeen and Duren families from the 1700s to the 20th century.
The bulk of the manuscript material is housed in the Correspondence Series, which chiefly consists of exchanges between members of the McKeen-Duren families. The earliest correspondence originates from New England, the McKeen family having been established in the area by brothers James, William, and Samuel McKeen, who emigrated to America from Ireland in the early 18th century. Beginning around 1823, letters exchanged between Silas McKeen and the father of Serena McKeen, who married Charles Duren, become more numerous. A significant portion of the correspondence was written by Silas to his son Charles, who served as a Union soldier during the Civil War. The family's exchanges then began to stretch westward during a period in which Philena and Phebe McKeen taught at the Western Female Seminary, Oxford, Ohio, and when Charles McKeen Duren moved to Iowa following the Civil War. Prominent topics in the letters from the latter half of the 19th century include Phebe and Philena's literary and publishing activities; education in New England and the Midwest; the Civil War and its effect on New England citizens; and routine family topics such as health, religion and morality, and social activities. There are very probably references to the abolition movement and slavery - the McKeens, Silas in particular, were outspoken abolitionists.
The family's penchant for a rich variety of written communication is also reflected in the numerous pieces in the Writings Series, which is divided into two subseries, Manuscripts and Volumes. The Manuscripts subseries contains handwritten copies of a variety of types of writing done by members of the McKeen-Duren family arranged in rough chronological order. The Volumes subseries contains often unattributed handwritten drafts and notes on fictional pieces; essays, probably written by Phebe or Philena; and sermons, most likely written by Silas McKeen. There may be material related to Silas McKeen's writings on slavery.
The collection is especially notable for its extensive Photographs Series. Almost all photographic media common to the 19th century can be found here, including many albumen prints, chiefly in the form of cartes-de-visite and cabinet cards; cyanotypes; and cased and uncased ambrotypes, daguerreotypes and tintypes. Also present are gelatin silver printing-out images or possibly platinum prints. The series is divided into four subseries: Albums, Cased Images, Oversize Prints, and Prints. A few of the albums originated from family trips to England and the Middle East. One family member, perhaps Phebe, was reportedly an avid amateur photographer, but direct evidence of this remains to be discovered. Interior photographs of the family's home show multitudes of photographs hung on the wall. Other subjects include family members from babyhood to old age, family friends, travel in England and the Middle East, pets, and horses. There are few landscapes but there is a sequence of images taken at Abbott Academy of buildings, grounds, and students with their teachers. Some of the photographic items, particularly the cased images, are fragile and should be handled with care.
The Diaries and Scrapbooks Series contains many personal journals and diaries, spanning the years 1804-1900, and scrapbooks, circa 1838-1902. The diaries are quite detailed and were chiefly written by the female members in the McKeen family; topics revolve around family health problems, visitors and travel, readings, the weather, and emotional or religious experiences. There may be passing references to slavery; there is one reference to a prominent abolitionist, later imprisoned, who visited the McKeen house. The scrapbooks house pasted-in clippings pertaining to family members, and many published short pieces written by Silas, Phebe, and Philena McKeen. There are also handwritten extracts of letters, as well as prescriptive pieces and poems, and a series of pages from Civil War periodicals. There are quite a few clippings in the scrapbooks on slavery and abolitionism, as well as references to issues pertaining to statehood; many of the anti-slavery pieces published in New England serials were written by Silas McKeen from the 1830s to the 1850s. The clippings folder in the Printed Material Series contains similar loose items.
The Financial Papers Series contains notifications of contributions to missionary institutions, receipts for good and services, society memberships, and subscriptions. A number of ledgers, some in bound volumes, are also found here.
The Genealogy Series contains extensive handwritten accounts and notes originating from the early 19th century, documenting the ancestry of the McKeen-Duren family and related branches, as well as two hand-written bound volumes containing detailed genealogies of the Duren, Gould, Prichard, and Freeman families. There are also printed materials, including obituaries and memorial pieces.
The Legal Papers Series contains the earliest documents, dated 1720, and includes land grants and deed transfers, inheritance inventories, loan notices, service contracts, wills and will abstracts, writs of indenture or apprenticeship, powers of attorney, and other documents.
An assortment of printed items, clippings, and ephemera pertaining to members of the McKeen-Duren family can be found in the Printed Materials Series, including invitations, event programs, announcements, obituaries and memorial pieces, short story reprints, copies of a course curriculum, a copy of the Abbot Academy journal, cards, and other assorted materials, including a hand-drawn map, perhaps the local vicinity where one of the families lived, found in the ephemera folder.
A folder of Oversize Material housing diplomas awarded to members of the McKeen-Duren families completes the collection.
Subject Headings
Abbott Academy (Andover, Mass.); Abolitionists -- Vermont; Antislavery movements -- United States -- History; Duren, Charles McKeen, 1842-1934; Duren family; Education -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Iowa -- Social life and customs; Massachusetts -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; McKeen family; McKeen Duren, Serena, 1819-1862; McKeen, Phebe F. (Phebe Fuller), 1831-1880; McKeen, Philena, 1822-1898; McKeen, Silas, 1791-1877; New England -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Photography -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Slavery -- Religious aspects; Slavery -- United States -- Periodicals; Slavery -- United States -- Public opinion; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Social aspects; United States -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Vermont -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Women -- Education -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Albumen prints; Ambrotypes; Cabinet cards; Cartes-de-visite; Clippings; Cyanotypes; Diaries; Daguerreotypes; Ephemera; Gelatin silver prints; Journals; Photograph albums; Postcards; Scrapbooks; Tintypes
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1816-1934 and undated, (7.5 boxes)
  This series starts off with a single folder of birthday "Certificates," letters written from Silas McKeen, Charles Duren, and Charles McKeen Duren to their children giving thanks and a description of the child on the occasion of his or her birthday. A significant portion of the correspondence falls during the United States Civil War period, 1861-1865 (17 folders); they were written mainly by Silas McKeen to his son Charles, who served in the Union Army. Exchanges from this period express the senders' thoughts on contemporary events and are sometimes written on stationery supporting the Union cause, and include passing references to slavery. A number of letters pertain to or are written by Freeman Duren, a family member who served in the 13th Regiment, Massachusetts Volunteers. There are very probably many more references to the abolition movement and slavery in the correspondence - the McKeens, Silas in particular, were abolitionists. Following the Civil War, the bulk of the correspondence generally belongs to members of the Duren family in Iowa, and refer to family matters, health and sickness, honors received by family members, and business. Themes of note include the teaching and education administration career of Philena McKeen, who was Principal of Abbot Academy, Andover, Massachusetts for 33 years (1859-1892). The literary career of Phebe McKeen, sister of Philena and a teacher at Abbot Academy, is also a notable topic of correspondences in the collection. From 1859 a number of the exchanges relate to Phebe's contributions to serial publications and several book-length works: Thornton Hall (1872), Theodora (1875, entitled Theodora Cameron when published in the United Kingdom circa 1878), The Little Mother and her Christmas (1876), Annals of Fifty Years: A History of Abbot Academy, Andover, Mass., 1829-1879 (1880, coauthored with her sister, Philena), and Sketch of the Early Life of Joseph Hardy Neesima (1890, published posthumously). A letter of particular note sent to Philena McKeen in March of 1892 is from the widow of Joseph Hardy Neesima, the first Japanese person to receive a degree from a western college, Amherst College, and founder of what would become Doshisha University in Kyoto, Japan; in it she thanks Philena for sending a copy of the book that Phebe McKeen had written about Joseph Hardy Neesima. Another letter of note comes from Harriet Beecher Stowe (1892 May 5), sent along with an autographed copy of Uncle Tom's Cabin for a new library/reading room that was constructed at Abbot Academy. Two letters, the first from an unidentified writer addressed to Miss McKeen (1890 Nov. 3) and the second from the widow of Joseph Hardy Neesima include cartes-de-visite photographs.
  - Certificates and correspondence, 1816-1859 (Box 1)
  - 1860-1864 (Box 2)
  - 1864-1869 (Box 3)
  - 1870-1873 (Box 4)
  - 1873-1877 (Box 5)
  - 1877-1880 (Box 6)
  - 1880-1897 (Box 7)
  - 1898-1934 and undated (Box 8)
- Diaries and Scrapbooks Series, 1804-1906 and undated, (2.5 boxes)
  Comprised of 19 volumes of varying sizes. The diaries and journals, described more fully below, were kept by various individuals in the McKeen family, mostly women, and span the years from 1804-1898; most are quite detailed. The scrapbooks house many clippings pertaining to family deaths or honors, publications written by family members, and other events relating to the McKeen-Duren families. In the scrapbooks probably kept by Silas McKeen from the 1830s through the 1850s, there are a number of clippings regarding abolitionism, slavery, and various political events relating to statehood, the Dred Scott Decision, and other national issues preceding the Civil War. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Journal, 1804-1806, [possibly Elizabeth Freeman Duren] (Box 8)
    Writer mainly expresses religious sentiments and interior experiences of unworthiness, guilt, and redemption; few personal names are mentioned.
  - Memo of ministerial service of Silas McKeen, 1815-1821, 1873, 1877 (Box 8)
    Memoranda documenting Silas McKeen's ministerial service; includes 1877 postscript regarding the monument erected to Silas after his death.
  - Sermon and topic book, 1842-1845 (Box 8)
    Silas McKeen's record of sermons and topics preached.
  - "Quotidiana, GWM", 1848 (Box 8)
    Diary, 1848, possibly written by George Whitefield McKeen, died in 1850 at age of 27. Comments on many events, education, and family routines, including visits by friends. Inscription on flyleaf reads "Marianne McKeen, 1840" - George's sister, died in 1845, age 23. Clipping on stereoscopic photography, 1855, Alfred Southworth, laid in back.
  - Diary, 1851 Jan.-1854 Mar. (Box 8)
    Title page reads, "Index Rerum," G. W. McKeen, Dartmouth College, Oct. 1843 N. H.," but first pages cut. Diary, 1851-1854, begins on page marked "29," entries written by a woman, possibly Serena, George's sister, as it mentions Philena and Phebe in the third person. Postscript from 1853 may be by a different hand, as it speaks of "our dear" Serena's illness after June 1851. Comments on page 40 that antislavery "martyr" Capt. [W?alker], came to dine; had been imprisoned and was evidently supported by the McKeens.
  - Diary of Eliza M. McCane, Western Female Seminary, Oxford, Ohio, 1858 April-July (Box 8)
    Seems to have been a teacher at the seminary. Mentions Phebe McKeen, missionary training and visits by missionaries, missionary work among Native Americans, and various school events and festivities.
  - Diary [Phebe F. McKeen], Waitsfield, Vt., 1852 May-1862 July (Box 8)
    The writer, Phebe McKeen, expresses many religious sentiments and practices much self-examination; entries also mention visits of family and friends, outings, the weather, and readings. The diary dwells at length on her sister Serena, who at the time was an invalid and died in 1862. Clipping about Civil War Vermont soldier laid in, also several religious notes.
  - Diary, Serena M. Duren, 1861 Jan.-1861 Dec. (Box 8)
    Small almanac diary which begins with the funeral for her daughter, Lizzie, who died at 14. Brief entries which follow note the weather, her own health and the sickness and death of others, outings, and visits. Small list of expenditures in back.
  - Diary, Serena M. Duren, 1862 Jan.-1862 May 5 (Box 8)
    Small almanac diary continues as above, with frequent mentions of ill health, daily weather, visits, and infrequent outings. Serena Duren died at age 43, July 1862.
  - Diaries, Silas McKeen, 1863 May 19-Dec. 9; 1864 Jan.-Dec. (Box 8)
    Small almanac diary for 1863 sewn to a larger farmer's almanac for 1864. The 1863 diary begins in May with a trip to Lowell (Vt.); subsequent entries are brief and chiefly note the comings and goings of family members, especially his children, his own church-related activities, and trips out of town. There are lists of addresses on the last few pages. The 1864 almanac's memoranda, which chiefly record Silas' travels, are even more brief.
  - Travel diaries, P. McKeen [Philena], Andover, Mass., Trip from the river St. Lawrence with Capt. Holmes and Miss Carrie and Mr. Edmund Holmes in 1867[followed by trip to Adirondacks, 1869], July 19-Aug. 19, 1869 July 30-Aug. (Box 9)
    Diary of pleasure trip down the St. Lawrence in summer 1867. Sketches, packing list, names and addresses, and expenses on last pages. Two dried plants laid in. Also includes notes on a trip to Adirondacks in August 1869. These trips were turned by Philena into published travel pieces pasted into a scrapbook in this collection.
  - Travel diary, Philena McKeen, Andover Mass., summer 1889 (Box 9)
    Trip to England and Switzerland with Charles, her brother, and one other woman. Almost certainly related to photo album from same geographical locations - see the Photographic Materials Series, as well as to published travel pieces appearing in a scrapbook in this collection. Currency conversions and detailed expenses included.
  - Journal, Andover, Mass., circa 1890s-1900 (many pages cut) [Philena?] (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks, 1838-1900s
    - Two scrapbooks, 1840s-1892 (Box 9)
      Contain much genealogical and biographical information regarding the McKeen family, including lengthy biographies of Serena and Marianne McKeen as well as extracts of letters describing the demise of various female individuals in the family, including the death of Silas McKeen's first wife in a carriage accident.
    - Five scrapbooks, 1838-1900s (Box 10)